Okay, so
OK?
we are starting an overview of Greek history.
...??????????????????????????????????????1?
Remember the story so far.
?????????????????????????????????????????..?????..????????????中????????????????????????????????中?????????中???前??????????????????????????..?????..??...??..??..??..??..??..??..??..?????..??..??..???…..??…..……..?
We talked about the Bronze Age and
我们谈到了青铜时代和
where Mycenaean Greece was trading
米凯尼希腊的希腊交易与世界的交流与战斗
and fighting with the rest of the world.
...
And then the Bronze Age collapse happened and
Mycenaean Greece came to an end.
...
And because of its destruction,
??
this allowed for massive innovation throughout Greece.
这使得希腊全境大创新
So we saw the introduction of the polis, the city -state.
这时出现了古希腊的城邦
We saw the beginning of the use of the alphabet.
我们见证了文字使用的起始。
And so literacy rates increased radically throughout Greece.
于是，文字普及全希腊，文字率大增。
And we saw Homer who gave us the Iliad
我们看见了荷马的《伊利亚》与《奥德赛》。
and the Odyssey.
我们看见了荷尔曼的...
So today,
译文1
I'm just going to go over the overview of Greek history,
译文2
mainly focusing on the polis.
主要以城邦为中心。
So one thing to understand about the polis is
翻译后句子句后再加上?
that geography is destiny.
那地理决定命运。
Geography is destiny.
地理决定命运。
And this basically means that
并且这基本意味着
your geography will determine the culture,
你的地理会决定文化
the economy, and
经济与
the political structure of your society.
你的社会的政治结构。
And we see that with the Greek polis.
我们在希腊的古典里看到的。
The Greek geography is very diverse.
希腊的地理很大。
There are mountains, there are rivers,
28. 这里有山脉，河流，平原与河岸。
there are plains, and there are coastlines.
29. 28????????????????????????????????????
And depending on where
]}We need to translate cues 28-30. They are: [28] There are mountains, there are rivers, [29] there are plains, and there are coastlines. [30] Anddepending on where ... (incomplete). We need to produce translations array with 3 strings. Use Chinese terms: 山脉, 河流, 平原, 河岸? but earlier they used
you are geographically in Greece,
你在地理上位于希腊，
you will have a different type of polis.
你会有不同的古典里。
And so the two classic examples are Sparta and Athens.
两者皆是古典里的两种典型。”
Sparta and Athens are the two most dominant polis in about the year 500 BC.
???
So let's first talk about Sparta.
So Sparta is located on the Pelonese.
???
This is Sparta.
这是萨尔帕。
And the land around Sparta is basically plains,
萨尔帕周围的土地基本是平原，
which makes it ideal for agriculture.
它们的土壤好好。”
Okay? So for most of its history,
好的？所以在它的历史大部分时间里，
Sparta was an agricultural nation.
萨尔帕是一个农业国。
And because
而且因为
it is ideal for agriculture,
它是农业的理想之地，
it needs people to work the land.
它需要人们去工作。
And through its conquest,
And through itsconquest,
Sparta developed a slave system.
...
Okay? And these people are called helots.
And helots are just slaves in Sparta
...
that work the land. They are farmers.
它们在耕地，农民们。
And these are people who have been conquered by Sparta.
这些人是被塞尔帕斯特拉的夺取。
And because there are so many helots, okay, the ratio is about 10 to 1.
因为它们有点儿…
So for every one helot, sorry, for every one Spartan, there's 10 helots.
...
Sparta had to become a military society in order to control the helots.
So it created an education system in
...
order to train its citizens to be soldiers.
以训练其公民成为士兵的目的。
So the system worked like this.
在此系统中，已然。
About age 7, you left your family
大约七岁时，离开了家…
and you were put into a boarding school where
在此时，您被送进了寄宿学校，那里…
you were watched over by kids who were older than you.
在此时……
Okay? Maybe 11 or 12.
...
And obviously, you put young kids with older kids,
the older kids will beat the crap out of these young kids
...
who are about 7 or 8. And
this instills the idea of emotional discipline into the system.
这为系统注入了情感纪律的概念。
And this is what happened to the children. Now, when these children became teenagers,
现在当时光回到后期……
they were paired with a mentor
………
who was maybe 25 to about 30, okay?
大约25到30岁，没错？
An older adult. And they became lovers.
一位年长的成年人。随后他们成了恋人。
The Spartans did not consider this homosexuality.
斯巴达人把它视作同一人间的情感联结。
We would consider it homosexuality.
...
But they themselves did not consider this homosexuality.
Okay? They just considered this as a
...
way to build emotional cohesion,
73. 方式构建情感连结，
love among its soldiers.
74. 其士兵间的情感情绪
And about age 18 or 19,
5. 约18岁/??
the students would graduate and
学生们毕业后会这样，他们会去结婚并组建自己的家庭。
they would go on to marry and have their own families.
但斯巴达士兵们都要一起吃饭。
But the Spartan soldiers were all required to eat together.
But the Spartan soldiers wereall required to eat together.
Okay? So the soldiers, even though they had families, they were still required to eat together.
好的？所以士兵们即使他们有家人，也仍需一起吃饭。
They were required to train together and to eat together.
他们又要训练一同，吃一同。
Spartans had no private property.
斯巴达士兵们没得有私财。
Everything, including the helots, belonged to everyone.
Okay? So it's basically like communism or proto -communism.
好的？它就是像百思通的百思通？
They had no money system.
...
They had no wealth. Everything belonged to everyone.
他们没有财富。全都归大家。
And it was a brutal state.
它是个繁忙的州
The Spartans were notorious for being brutal people.
斯巴达人以其繁忙的方式而闻名。
So an example is the helots.
斯巴达人以此例为其繁忙的能量。
So they had a campaign of terror to maintain control over the helots.
So young soldiers would often be
...
required to patrol at night.
Okay? They would maybe lie in the fields.
Okay? 他们可能在田里休息
Because now and then, some helots would break curfew.
...
They would, at midnight, try to sneak out and have some fun.
And if you, as a Spartan young man,
...
saw a Spartan, you would say, I saw a helot be out at night.
saw a Spartan, you would say,I saw a helot be out at night.
Well, they would kill you.
好的，先前的字幕翻译已完成。请在此处翻译以下字幕：
They would take out a knife and stab you in the neck. Okay? And
翻译后可用来回到?
this was meant to instill terror
这个词句...
in the helots to prevent them from rebelling.
...
Okay? But the problem is, because there were so
好的，...
many helots, and the Spartans were so brutal,
...
rebellions and revolutions would break out often.
Okay? So this created a society
OK? 这句...??
which focused on the helots.
翻译...
And this focused on maintaining control in the Pelonese.
??
So the Spartans were not at all interested in foreign policy.
...
Okay? They had absolutely no interest in the world outside Sparta.
OK? 这句...??
The Spartans, as a culture, was very conservative.
...
Okay? They liked the way that...
OK? 这句...??
They liked the way...
他们喜欢那种方式...
They wanted things to stay the way...
他们想要让它们保持那样的...
They are. So it was a very conformist culture.
他们是的。所以它是一种非常符合的文化。
Now and then you had some kings or individuals
现在...??
who tried to change society.
谁尝试改变社会。
The Spartans would kill those people.
斯巴达人会杀死那些人。
Okay? You were not allowed to question authority.
好的？你们不允许提问权威。
You were not allowed to promote change in Sparta.
好的，...??
The Spartans were also isolationists.
斯巴达人也是孤立主义者。
Okay? Their entire society was a society of isolationists.
好的？他们的整个社会是孤立主义者的社会。
Their entire policy was, if you leave us alone, we'll leave you alone.
他们的全部政策是：如果你们把我们留着，我们就把你们留着。
Okay? And so that
OK? 这就是…
was the society of Sparta.
是斯巴达的社会。
When you think about it, in many ways,
当你思考时，在多种方式里，
it's very much like China throughout its history.
它在历史上很久的相似。”
Okay? So the analogy is China,
好的？所以这个类比是中国，
which China has always been, throughout its history,
中国在整个历史里一直如此，
very conservative and very isolationist.
非常保守且很久久的孤立主义者。
China is just not interested in the outside world. Why? Because
中国只是在点儿…
it's focused on maintaining
...
control over its peasantry.
Okay? There's too much internal chaos.
好的？内部混乱太多了。
China just is not interested in the outside world.
中国只是不关心外部世界。
So China, for its history, has both been conservative, does not like change.
所以说中国在历史上既保守又不喜欢变革。
Okay? And very isolationist.
好的？又非常孤立。
It's not concerned about the outside world.
它不关心外部世界。
Does that make sense, guys? Any questions so
那算得了吗，大家？
far about Sparta before I move on to Athens?
离开了...??
Okay. So Athens was a completely opposite society to Sparta.
...??
And the reason why, again, is geography.
This is Sparta. Sorry, this is Athens.
这就是斯巴达。抱歉，这就是雅典。
And Athens is in Attica.
而且雅典在阿特提卡。
And it's by the coast.
而且它在海岸边。
And Athens, the countryside is very hilly.
安德亚特，乡村非常多山地。
So it's bad for growing crops.
好吧，种植种植??
But Athens has two major advantages.
又...??
The first major advantage is it has a very good harbor.
第一大优势是它有一个非常好的港口。
Okay? And also,
好的？还有，
it's hilly.
它是多山的。
But the hilly terrain is actually good for growing olive trees.
但多山的地形实际上适合种植橄榛树。
Okay? Olives. It's also very good at pottery.
??
So because of this, Athens,
for most of its history, focused on trade.
在其大部分历史中，专注于贸易。
Right? It was a trading nation.
对吧？它是个贸易国。
And because they are traders and merchants, they are also very good at trading.
而且因为它们是商人，故又善于交易。
So they have a very different culture to the Spartans.
??
Okay? So the first thing is they're very expansionist.
Okay? They're aggressive. And
??
the idea here is the Athens will go and seek out new markets.
在此，雅典将去寻找新市场。
They also plant new
他们也在亚得里亚海里种植新殖民。
colonies throughout the Aegean.
在亚得里亚海里种植新殖民
To the west is the Aegean Sea.
西方是爱琴海。
To the south is the Mediterranean.
南方是地中海。
Okay? And they will plant colonies throughout this area.
好的？他们会在此区布置殖民。
And they have to encourage their citizens to go out
and explore the world in order to find new markets,
和...以便于探索世界，寻找新市场
in order to bring goods and
和...以便于探索…
ideas back to Athens.
...
Okay? Because
OK
Athens was expansionist,
its cultural system,
其文化系统
its cultural beliefs was very different.
其文化信仰很久?
From the Spartans.
从...??
Okay? So whereas the Spartans were very conservative,
OK? 这里...??
the Athenians had a policy,
had a belief in the idea of eudaimonia.
有一种信念，认为eudaimonia是...??
Eudaimonia. So
?
eudaimonia is a Greek word
eudaimonia是希腓词
and it means human flourishing.
Flourishing. And
繁荣。和
the idea here is to be the best that you can be.
这里的意思是让你能成为最好的自己。
All right? So the example of eudaimonia,
好的，回到...??
the most famous example of eudaimonia is this.
...??
In Homer's Iliad, the main character is Achilles.
在《伊利亚特》中，主角是阿基琼斯。
And Achilles is the best warrior of the Greeks against Troy.
阿基琼斯是希腓人对阵海神的最佳战士。
And Achilles says this in the book.
阿基琼斯在书中这么说。
He says, before I came to Troy, I saw a prophet.
他在说之前，我去到达里亚之前，看到了一个…
I saw a fortune teller and he told me my fortune.
我看到一位算命师，他告诉我我的命运。
He said I could choose to not come to Troy.
他给我一个选择：可以不去到达里…
And live to be a, live a very long,
我方…
healthy life.
健康的生活。
But I'd be a nobody.
但我会是个没名气的…
If I came to Troy, I would die young, but I would die as a hero.
如果…
I would be remembered by everyone.
我会被大家记住。
Everyone would sing of my glory and my triumph.
大家会唱起我的光荣与胜利。
So that was my choice. I could live for a very long time and just be a nobody.
于是我作此选择。
Or I could be a hero and die young.
译文1
And he said, well for me, that's not a choice.
译前后????????????????????????????????????????????????
Okay? For me,
]}We need to translate cues 197-199. Provide JSON array translations. Each string may contain at most one newline. Use Chinese terms. Let's translate: 197:
to be alive means to achieve eudaimonia.
...
I have to be the best that I can be.
???
And therefore, my only option is to come to Troy
]?We need to translate cues 201-202. Provide JSON array with two translations. Let's read cues: 201: I have to...? 202: And...? Let's translate. Need to produce Chinese subtitles. Use terms. Let's craft translations. 201:
and die a hero.
...
Okay? And that's the mentality in Athens.
It is much better to die young as a hero
We have…………………??…???
than to live a long time as a nobody.
...
Whereas in Spartans, we're the complete opposite.
???
Okay? It's just better to be a nobody and
get along with everyone than it is to die as a hero.
与大家相处比当英雄更重要。
Okay? So very opposite societies.
好的？所以两种社会截然不同。
But, and what this did, this idea of eudaimonia,
但这件事让雅典成为了一个非常竞争的社会。
it made Athens into a very competitive society.
Okay? Because if everyone's trying to achieve eudaimonia,
好的？因为如果大家都在追求幸福，就会有很多竞争。
then you're going to have a lot of competition.
好的？如果大家都在追求幸福，就会有…
Okay? Because they're going to be one hero.
好的？因为他们将成为一位英雄。
Everyone cannot be a hero.
每个人都不能是英雄。
They're going to be one hero.
他们将成为一位英雄。
So again, the example is Homer's Iliad.
再一次，例子就是《荷马的《伊利亚特》》。
And when Achilles got into a fight with Agamemnon,
当时，艾里奥斯在与阿甘莫姆的斗争中…
Achilles basically says, I don't like you.
艾里奥…
You're a dog. I'm not going to fight for you.
...
And Agamemnon says, I don't need you.
阿里奥斯…
What Achilles did was, he went to his mother,
阿里奥…
who was a goddess, and
谁是个…………………………………………………
Achilles said to Thetis, his mother,
?
could you please get the gods to help the Trojans
请你们给我方位…
so that
]}We need to translate cues 226 and 227. They are: [226] could you please get the gods? Wait actual cue:
Agamemnon would have to come beg for my help against the Trojans.
阿甘美农要去乞求我的帮助去对付特洛伊人。
Okay? He was basically committing treason.
好的，?
And in the Greek world, you're allowed to do that
在希腊里………………………………………………………………………………
because the most important thing is eudaimonia.
?
To achieve eudaimonia.
实现 eudaimonia。
Okay? Does that make sense? It's a very weird world, but
“可”??…
in Athens, it's extremely competitive where
在雅典里极其竞争，大家都在争抢后方以成英雄。
everyone's trying to backstab each other in order to become the hero.
在雅典里极其竞争…
And because of this, because there's so much competition,
在此之下，因为……………………………………………………
Athens created a new system called ostracize.
...
Okay? So the idea here is, because
the Athenians were so at each other's throat,
...
if someone was breaking the rules,
or if someone was being too competitive in the pursuit of eudaimonia,
如果有人在追求幸福时过于竞争，
the Athenian people could choose to ostracize this person.
在此时，雅典人们可选…
And what this meant was, you'd be banished,
okay, banished or exiled
...
from Athens for ten years.
从 10 里…
And this was considered even worse than death.
...
Okay, this punishment was worse than death.
OK? 这…
The reason why is, in the Polish system,
翻译结果
the only people that mattered were citizens.
...
Okay? And
the Greek world was very chauvinistic,
希腊世界很自大…
or closed, which meant that you could not be,
...
you could not earn the right to be a citizen.
你可以不赚得成为公民的权利。
You had to be born to become a citizen.
我想…
You understand? You had to be born into citizenship.
You understand? You had tobe born into citizenship.
You could not become a citizen for your own hard work
...
and for your merit. Okay, does that make sense?
So in other words, if you were banished from your Polish, you became a nobody.
...
You were basically dead to everyone.
Because only citizens had rights in the Greek world.
因为只有公民在希腊世界里有权利。
If you were a slave, or you were a foreigner, you had absolutely no rights.
...
You could not own land, you could not even speak in public.
你可以在此时...
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好的？这有道理吗？全部好啦。
Um, so,
嗯，...
Athens was a democracy.
雅典是一个民主政体。
Where everyone had the right to speak and to vote.
在此时，人人可发言并投票。
Okay? But really, when we talk about democracy in this world,
好的？但实际上，当我们谈论这个世界的民主时，
we're not saying that everyone could become president, or everyone could become a leader.
我们又不说每个字母…
Really, political power can only be held by people of,
真的，政治力量只会被…
um, nobility.
嗯…
Okay? So democracy usually was a battle between
好的？民主通常是贵族不同派别之间的较量。
different factions of the nobility.
好的，回到…
Usually between the upper nobility,
通常在上层贵族与下层贵族之间
and the lower nobility.
Okay? And this is a lesson that's true throughout history.
好的？这是一段贯穿历史的课题。
Okay? So remember, usually we think history,
好的，回到…
societies, um, the conflict is between the haves and the have -nots.
Right? The poor and the rich.
右？贫穷与富裕。
All right? Haves
好吧，先前的…
versus have -nots.
再…
Whatever you do, what I would teach you in this class, one important thing I would teach you in this class is, this is not true.
任意...??
Okay? When you look at history,
好的，回到…
the conflicts in society are
...
usually between the have a lot
通常在有很多的之间
and have somewhat more.
和 … … …
Does that make sense? Okay?
那算得了吗？好吧？
It's usually between the have a lot
…
versus the have some
对比………………
but I want more.
...
Okay? And throughout history, we call these people different names.
好的？并且在历史上我们把这些人叫作不同的名字。
So, um,
]}We need to translate cue [290] and [291] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations in order. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use preferred terms. Let's translate: [290]
in this society, these are basically the low nobility.
in this society, these arebasically the low nobility.
Okay? These are the nobility who have money
?
but they want more.
在这社会里，低级贵族是...
Okay? And, um,
?
in the French Revolution,
in the ... ...
we'll call them the petite bourgeoisie.
...
And today, we call them the middle class.
Okay? Does that make sense? The poor people do not rebel.
OK? 这算是个好例子吗？这…………………??
They might riot, but they do not revolt.
?
It's usually the middle class, or the low nobility,
or the petite bourgeoisie that revolt.
或小资产阶级的起义。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好的？这有道理吗？一切都好。
So, Athens is a democracy and
于是，雅典是个民主制。
it's usually a conflict between the upper nobility and the lower nobility.
它通常是上层贵族与下层贵族之间的冲突。
Um, Sparta is an oligarchy.
嗯，斯巴达是个奥尔格拉奇。
Okay? Which is, basically, means ruled by the few.
好的？它们的意思是………??
And they hate democracy. So, so,
和他们又相互相互……
these systems, these cultures, Sparta and Athens,
...
are diametrically opposed to each other.
They hate each other. Uh, they're always in conflict with each other.
他们相互相互…………………
Okay? Does that make sense? Any questions so far about Sparta and Athens?
...
Are you guys clear about this?
These two different cultures?
这些两种不同的文化？
All right. So, this is about the year 500 BCE.
好的，回到 500 年前的那一段时间。
Um, around this time, the Greeks are colonizing,
好的，回到 314 句...
uh, the Mediterranean and the Aegean.
嗯，地中海与爱琴海。
Okay? And this territory
好的，地中…
belongs to Persia.
...
The Persian Empire is
波斯帝国是
considered one of the greatest empires
波斯帝国被认为是人类历史上最伟大的帝国之一。
ever in human history. We will do the Persian Empire, uh, later this semester.
我们将在本学期稍后做波斯帝国。
Okay? But I want to focus on the Greeks for now.
好的？但我现在想先聚焦希腊人。
All you need to know is,
全是个别的要知道的。
the Persian Empire spread throughout most of the world,
波斯帝国在百里里…
including Egypt, uh, Mesopotamia,
...
um, and what we call Iran today.
Okay? It was a huge, huge empire
...
that was extremely enlightened
那是极其开明的
for its age.
那是个很好的…
Okay? It was really considered, uh, the best empire at that time.
...
Uh, um, and there were Greeks who lived
2024-10-12 1/1/…
in, uh, Anatolia or what they call Asia Minor back
? 1/…
then. The thing about the Persian Empire is,
…
if you were a subject city, you could do whatever you want, but you have to pay taxes.
如果你是一个城邦，你可以随心所欲，但你必须交税。
And these people did not like to pay taxes.
这些人不喜欢交税。
So, they revolted.
于是他们起义。
And, and this is the reason why they revolted.
338. 这就是为什么他……
they went to Sparta and to Athens and sought help.
]}We need to translate cues 338-340. Provide JSON array translations. Eachstring may contain newline. Use simplified Chinese. Let's translate: 338:
Okay? They basically said, look, we're all Greeks, uh,
. Actually cue 338:
we're being oppressed by the Persians, could you please help us?
我们正被波斯人压迫，能否请你们帮忙？
What did the Spartans say? What was the Spartan response?
斯巴达的回答是什么？
No. Because we don't care, okay?
不，正因为如此才会去…
Your problem, not my problem.
你的问题，不是我的问题。
Well, and what did the Athenians say?
好，先说下希腊的说法？
Yeah, sure. Let's achieve eudaimonia, man.
是的，没错！
Let's be Achilles. Let's go over
让我们扮演阿基琉斯。我们先去……
and help them and maybe make a lot of money for ourselves, okay?
让我方去帮他们，且可为自己赚大钱，嗯？
So, because the Persian Empire was so powerful,
...
they destroyed the rebellion, okay?
他们在破灭叛乱后，好的？
And, in 490 BCE,
在公元前490年，
uh, the Persians decided to attack Greece to teach the Athenians a lesson.
在公元前490年，...
And this was called the Battle of Marathon.
并且这就是马拉松之战。
And in the Battle of Marathon, um, we actually don't know that much about it,
在马拉松之战里，嗯，咱们还没能给它写个好句子。
The sourcing is very limited.
来源很少。
But, what they say, okay, is,
但，所说的，好的，正是：
in the Battle of Marathon,
在马拉松之战里，
there are about 10,000 Athenians versus 25,000 Persians.
有大约一万名古希腊里士兵，约一万五千个回到。
That's a huge advantage for the Persians, right?
那是对古波人有大优势吧？
Well, the Athenians destroyed the Persians,
好，古波里士兵们又回到。
okay? The Athenians lost about 192 men.
好的，古波里士兵们回到。
The Persians lost about 5,000.
...】】}??
It was a slaughter. And a lot of the reason why is in the Battle of Marathon, the Persians used military tactics.
. ……… … ? … ??… …… -…… … … -…… ? … … … We need to translate cues 362-364. Provide JSON array translations. Let's translate each cueinto Simplified Chinese, following style. Use line breaks if needed. Provide exactly three translations. Let's craft them. Cue 362:
So, the Persian Empire
. ……… … ? … ??… ……-…… … … -…… ? … … …
is huge.
]}We need to translate cues 362-364. We havecues 362, 363, 364? Let's read. The prompt:
Okay? Lots of flat land.
...
And in this geography,
the, your main advantage is
...
cavalry, right? Horse archers.
That's what the Persians were known for.
...
Men on horses who would run around and shoot arrows at you.
Okay? The geography of Greece was different.
OK?
It was hilly. So,
它是丘陵的。
you didn't really use cavalry.
...
It was more mainly infantry fighting against each other.
It was more mainly infantryfighting against each other.
What the Greeks did over hundreds of years
什么是百年间希腊所做的事
was develop a new military tactic called hoplites.
可算作一条??
So hoplite comes from the word hoplin.
所以，重装步兵来自于“hoplin”一词。
Hoplin is Greek for shield.
希腊的重装步兵就是从“hoppin”一词。”
So these are men with large shields and spears.
这些人手持大盾牌与长矛。
The way they fought was using the phalanx formation.
他们的作战方式是用磅磅阵形。
The innovation of the phalanx was it was basically a wall.
第 382 句：...
So men would stand together and
...
behind each other so that they made a wall.
behind each other sothat they made a wall.
And because they had these shields and spears, it was a moving wall.
在此时，...
And the Persians didn't have armor.
And the Persiansdidn't have armor.
So when men of armor went to battle with men without armor,
...
usually armor wins. So the Greeks,
通常装甲能赢，故希腊里人…
the Athenians, destroyed the Persians at the Battle of Marathon.
在此时…
That made the Persians even more angry.
那让波斯人更愤怒。
So in about 480 BCE,
在公元前480年左右，
Persia organized a massive
波斯人组织了一支大规模的进攻部队对付希腊里人。
invasion force against Greece.
And this massive invasion force, again.
和这支大规模的进攻部队，再次出现。
The numbers,
...
the data, we can't confirm it.
根据数据，我们无法确认。
But we think it's about half a million people.
但我们认为大约有五十万名士兵。
Half a million soldiers.
五十万名士兵。
That's huge. Okay?
那很大。
But not only that, you had a huge navy. And
...
basically Persia called on every nation
of its empire to fight against Greece.
其帝国的部队去与希腊作战。
Which included Egypt.
包括埃及。
Which included the Phoenicians.
包括腓尼亚人。
Which also included Greeks.
哪一也包括希腊人。
Which also included Greeks. And they lived in the territory of Persia.
哪一也包含希腊人。并且在希腊之地。
And these Greeks are called the Ionian Greeks.
并且希腊人也被称为伊奥尼亚希腊人。
So it was a massive invasion force.
于是它是一支大规模的进攻部队。
And Sparta and
而且希腊人也被称为伊奥尼亚希腊人。
Athens became allies to resist the Persian invasion.
帕斯特里亚里奥斯的帕斯特里奥斯
But there were also some Greek policies that
但也有一些希腊政策与之并肩，包含底比斯。
sided with the Persians, including Thebes.
好的，北方的马可里奥斯…
Okay? The Macedonians to the north was also a big part of the invasion.
...
And also siding with the Persians.
又与伊波里亚人结盟。
So the invasion came north from Macedonia down here.
于是从马可里奥斯向下方的地中去。
And you may have heard of the Battle of Thermopylae.
又可见到百里可里奥斯的百里可里奥古…
The Thermopylae. This was made famous by a movie called 300.
热尔玛尔·帕尔帕尔…
I'm not sure if you've seen the movie 300. Okay?
...
But basically it was about 300 Spartans and
about 5,000 other Greeks who
约5,000名其他希腊人试图抵御波斯入侵。
tried to make a stand against the Persian invasion.
他们又在此处建墙。”】}We need to translate cues 420-422. They are two lines? Actually cues: [420] about 5,000 other Greeks who [421] tried to make a stand againstthe Persian invasion. [422] And they got destroyed. Okay? So three cues. Need three translations. Use simplified Chinese. Use terms: Greek=希腊人? Actually
And they got destroyed. Okay?
Wait previous translation used
So the Spartans, so the Persians came in
约5,000名其他希腊人试图抵御波斯入侵。
and the Greeks decided, okay, you know what?
他们又在此处建墙。”】}We need to translate cues 423-425. Provide three translations. Ensure Chinese. Use simplified. Let's craft. Cue 423:
Their numbers are so much bigger than ours.
. Actually context: [423] So the Spartans, so the Persians came in. Need Chinese:
Let's retreat. Okay? Back to Sparta.
约5,000名其他希腊人试图抵御波斯入侵。
And here at Corinth,
他们又在此处建墙。”】}We need to translate 3 cues. Let's produce. Use simplified Chinese. Ensure each translation string may contain at most one newline. Providethree translations. Let's craft: 1) 约5,000名其他希腊人试图抵御波斯入侵。 2) 他们又在此处建墙。 3) 他们又在此处建墙。 Wait duplicate. Actually cues: 426, 427, 428. So translations: 426:
they decided to build a wall to stop the Persian invasion.
? Let's produce.426:
The problem though is Athens is here.
约5,000名其他希腊人试图抵御波斯入侵。
Okay? So the Persians came in and burned down Athens. Now.
他们又在此处建墙。
What's important to understand is the Greeks have the concept of polis.
It's not a place.
它不是一个地方。
It's a community. Okay?
它是一个社区。好吗？
A polis is wherever the Greeks choose to be.
一个波斯城就是希腊人选择的地方。
So what happened that's very interesting is even
So what happened that'svery interesting is even
though the Athens came to destroy,
[436] 但也有可能在此处建墙。
sorry, even though Persia came to destroy Athens,
[437] 先前，先前！
the Athenians just got into their ships.
the … … ...
Okay? They just boarded their ships because Athens is a naval power
...
and they just sailed away.
他们刚刚离开船去航行
Okay? Do you understand? So Athens was not destroyed.
好的，船只离开船去航行
The city of Athens was destroyed, but not the community,
雅典城被毁，但城邦未灭
the polis of Athens.
雅典城被毁，城邦未消亡
And so, but now the Greeks are in a lot of trouble.
...
Okay? Because
what the Persians can
now do is
...
basically take their ships
and sail around and attack Sparta from behind.
和...船只...
And this is a huge problem for Sparta.
And this is a hugeproblem for Sparta.
Because what happens? Why?
因为...???
What is Sparta's ultimate weakness?
什么是斯巴达的终极弱点？
Why is it so easy to defeat Sparta in a war?
为什么在战斗中能很容易地战胜斯巴达？
What's the problem? Do you guys remember?
...
What are the Spartans really afraid of?
The helots, right? Okay?
赫洛特人，没错吧？
The helots. Remember, there's 10 helots for every one Spartan.
赫洛特人。记得有十个赫洛特人对应一个斯巴达人。
And the helots hate the Spartans because the Spartans are terrorizing,
和赫洛特人因为斯巴达人恐吓他们而相互相互相互相互相互相互相互相互相互相互相互相相相相相相相相相相
have terrorized them for centuries.
...
So all that Persia has to do now, okay?
460. 现在，...??
Very easy, is take their ships,
460??????
land on Sparta, and build forts,
陆上进攻斯巴达，建造城堡，防御设施，赫洛特人便会冲进来。
defenses, and the helots would run into them.
陆上进攻斯巴达，建造城堡，防御设施】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】】?】】?】?】?】…
Then the king, King Xerxes of Persia says,
然后，王国王王国王...
I, the benevolent king of Persia,
...
declare the helots to be free people now.
Now you have a revolution, okay?
现在你们有了革命，行吗？
The helots are now armed by the Persians.
赫尔奥特人已被波斯人武装。
And guess what? The Persians are going to, the helots are going to kill the Spartans.
波斯人已在此时…
Okay? Game over, okay? You understand?
好的？游戏结束，好的？你明白吗？
The war is over.
战斗已结束。
That's all the Persians have to do.
那就是波斯人要做的事。
Take their ships, sail around to the coast of Sparta,
取他们的船，绕行至萨拉的海岸，
build forts and defenses so that the helots can run to them,
取船后再建造船舱?
give the helots weapons, and then
?
let the helots run loose against the Spartans, and the war is over.
让海尔托斯自由奔跑对抗萨普兰的斗争，战斗已完！
Greece is forever destroyed.
Greece … … 中…… 先…… 先… 先… 字幕 … 先… ?? ?? ??
Okay? You understand? Very simple, right?
… … ... … ??… …… 翻 … … ... … 翻…
The Persians did not do that.
帕提亚人没有这么做。
Okay? The Persian king,
好的？帕提亚王，
King Xerxes, had a war council.
帕提亚国王克塞尔斯，有一次战争会议。
And there were a lot of generals who said to King Xerxes,
还有许多将军向克塞尔斯王说，
King, we've won the war.
克塞尔斯王，咱们已赢了！
Okay? We're all over Greece. We have half a million men in Greece.
好的，咱们已过了咸里！
There's nothing the Greeks can do about this.
有些事是希腊人自己能做的。
Okay? So, the Persians were feeling very confident.
...
And the Greeks,
...??
the Greek navy was on an island called Salamis.
希腊海军在萨拉米斯岛上。
Okay? Salamis. And everyone was freaking out.
萨拉米斯，大家都在忙着。
Okay? And what the Spartans wanted to do was say,
...
let's take our navy and defend the coastline of Sparta.
我们把舰队调往萨拉米斯，去守住萨拉米斯岛。
Because we know the Persians are going to invade Sparta at some point.
我们把舰船去调到萨拉有点儿。
They're going to land their ships on Sparta.
我们把舰船去调到萨外
Let's take our navy and
把我们的舰队调去
defend Sparta.
萨拉米斯岛，去守住萨拉米斯岛。
There was one Athenian general, okay?
His name is Phemistocles.
他的名字是佩菲斯托克斯。
Phemistocles. And he said, okay.
佩菲斯托克斯。然后他又说：
You know what? That's great for you guys.
你们知道吗？我好像…
Okay? But remember, our city, Athens, has been destroyed.
好的？但记得，我的城——雅典——已被毁灭。
We need to take on the Persians head on.
...??
We can't wait. And the Spartans are like,
OK? 先后………………
yeah, that's fine.
是的，没问题。
But the outnumber is three to one.
但人数比我们多三倍。
They have three more ships. They have three ships for every one ship we have.
他们有三艘船。
There's no way we can beat them in a naval battle.
还有没有什么能在海上打赢的？
And Phemistocles says, we either fight the Persians now
又...??
and achieve eudaimonia or we, Athens, we'll be like, okay.
...
Screw you, Spartans. We're going to go take our ship and
塞尔·尤，斯帕塔人。我们要去拿船去...
sail off west to Sicily or Africa.
塞尔...??】}We need to translate cues [509-511]. Provide JSON array. Let'stranslate. We need to produce Chinese subtitles. Let's think: cue 509:
Who cares? Okay? But we're going to go away.
. Wait actual cue: [509] Screw you, Spartans. We're going to go take our ship and [510] sail off west to Sicily or Africa. [511] Who cares? Okay? But we’re going to…? Wait [511] is
And we're going to leave the Persians to kill you guys.
...
Okay? So Spartans say, no, we don't have a choice but to listen to Athenians and fight.
Then what Phemistocles did was he sent a spy to King Xerxes.
...
And King Xerxes was having this war council about what to do.
And most of his generals were like, James, you're going to die.
...
My great king, we've won the war.
Let's just take our ships and attack Sparta and the war is over.
让我们把船只拿出来，去攻打斯帕特里亚? 只要...??
Okay? Then a spy sent by Phemistocles says to King Xerxes,
]}We need to translate cues 518 and 519. Provide JSON arraytranslations. Ensure Chinese natural. Let's translate: 518:
oh, great king,
哦，伟大王者，
the entire Greek navy is stuck in Salamis.
...
But they want to run away.
但他们想跑掉。
Now's your chance to attack them and destroy the Greek navy once and for all.
现在是你们去攻打他们并把希腊船只一一全打完的机会。
Okay? And at this point, King Xerxes says, no.
OK? 让我们先……??
I made the decision to send his entire navy,
]}We need..???…???……??……..?????……………??……..??……..??……………………..??…..??…??………………..??……..
okay, to destroy the Greek navy at Salamis.
好的，去在萨拉米斯摧毁希腊船只。
And his generals were like, don't do that, man.
他的将军们说：我不再去做这事。”
That's a risk you don't have to take.
那是你可以不做的风险。
Why do that? Why take the Greeks on?
为什么要做这件事？
Why fight the Greeks head on
为什么要先发起手工？
when we can just starve them out?
我想要去做……??????…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…?????
And King Xerxes said, no,
?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????
I came to defeat the Greeks.
我来征服希腊。
Okay? I'm the great king.
我好好！…???????
I want to defeat them at Salamis.
我想要去…
And build a monument to celebrate my great victory over the Greeks.
并建造一座纪念碑以庆祝我对希腊的伟大胜利。
My father, King Darius, set an army in 490 B.C.
我的父亲， 先后 先后 地 先后 先后 译????????????????????????????????????????????????……??……………………??…??…………??………??…??…??……???
And the Athenians killed or destroyed his army at Marathon.
…
I'm going to prove I'm a greater king than
我正在证明我比父亲更伟大，在萨拉米斯战胜希腊。
my father by defeating the Greeks at Salamis.
好的，我先前往去！
Okay? I don't want this war of attrition, this slow war.
好的，先前往去！
I want one great battle so that history will remember me forever.
我想要一场大胜，便可让历史记住我。
Okay? So he sends his entire force,
好的，先前…………………………………
about a thousand ships, to Salamis.
…
And Salamis, it's a strait, okay?
...
It's very narrow. So the ships have to line up and attack the Greeks one by one.
Okay? And at Salamis,
...
in a headlong battle, okay,
在一场大冲突中，...
the Greek ships were heavier and the Greek ships were manned by hoplites with armor.
...
And in this battle of Salamis,
the Greeks destroyed the Persian navy. Okay? Do you understand?
希腊人击沉波斯海军。好吗？你明白吗？
The Persian army had won the war.
波斯军已赢得战事。
And at Salamis, they lost the war.
在萨拉米斯，波斯军赢得了战事。
Okay? Now the problem is, now
好的？现在问题是，现在
that the Persian navy has been destroyed,
那波斯海军已被击沉，
supply lines are in trouble.
供给线已在困境中。
Okay? Do you understand? Because Greece is very poor.
好的？你明白吗？因为希腊很贫穷。
Greece is a very poor nation.
希腊是个很贫穷的民族国家。
You cannot resupply yourself in Greece.
你在希腊里可不再补给。
How do you feed half a million people?
一半百万人怎么喂饱？
Well, you need to bring in supplies from Persia.
好吧，得把波斯的补给送进来。
But now your navy has been destroyed.
但现在波斯海军已被击沉。
So now King Xerxes freaks out and he goes home.
translations
He's like, you know what? I burned down Athens.
???
That's good enough for me. Okay? And he leaves his cousin,
????
General Mardonis, to fight the Greeks.
将马尔多尼斯将军派去与希腊作战。
Okay? And at this point,
好吧，到了此时，
Mardonis could have chosen to not fight the Greeks.
马尔多尼斯可在此时选择不与希腊作战。
Right? Because Athens has been destroyed.
好的？因为雅典已被毁灭。
And Sparta is still there.
而且百里宫已在此。
It's still under threat. So
它还在百里宫里。
all Mardonis had to do was, he was in Thebes.
所有马尔多尼斯要做的就是， 他在底比斯。
Okay? He was in Thebes. All he had to do was stay in Thebes
好的，马尔多之前在底比车里？
and wait out the war. Okay?
其…
This is what we call a war of attrition, where you wait out the other enemy
这是一场…
because the other enemy has basically less resources than you.
...
Okay? Does that make sense? Again, really easy for the Persians to win.
But Mardonis chose to fight the Greeks at the Battle of the Thracians.
翻译1
The Battle of Palatia.
翻译2
And here, it was about equal forces,
翻译…
100,000 Greeks versus 100,000 Persians.
...
And the Greeks destroyed the Persians.
The Persians lost five times
...
more men than the Greeks.
更多的...
Okay? And
...
General Mardonis was killed in this battle.
第586条：将军马尔多尼斯在此战中阵亡。
So this war that the Persians should have won very easily,
第587条：此战…
the Persians lost.
帕尔西人失利。
And were completely destroyed.
并全然消灭。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？那算得了吗？
Okay, any questions so far about the Persian invasion?
好的，先前的英文句子里有点…
Okay. And because of this war,
好的。因这场战争，希腊已变得极其富裕。
Greece now became extremely wealthy.
好的，希腊已变得极其富裕。
The reason why is Persia is forced to retreat from Asia Minor
因为...
and the Greeks were able to capture a lot of treasure.
...
Okay? Now,
好的？现在，
after this, Persia switches strategies.
在此之后，帕萨里改换策略。
Okay? Persia never again invades Greece because they think this is stupid to invade Greece.
好的，帕萨里再也不再发起…
Okay? But the Greeks don't know this.
好的，...??
The Greeks think, okay, the Persians will come back at any point.
?????????..??
Okay? So the Athenians say,
?..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..
let's take the battle to Persia.
我们把战斗搬到帕萨里去。
And what do the Spartans say?
那时，斯巴达人说了？
The Spartans say, no. We're going to go home and that's it.
斯巴达人说：我们去回家去。
Okay? So to battle against the Persians,
好的？ 于是把战斗去到...??
the Athenians create something called the Delian League.
????????????????????????????????????????
The Delian League is a defensive alliance between Athens
]}We need to translate cues 605-607. Provide translations array with 3strings. Use Chinese. Ensure line breaks natural. Let's translate: 605:
and these colonies and islands in the Aegean.
...
And the idea is if the Persians come back,
we will master forces and fight the Persians at sea.
...
The problem is that only Athens had a navy.
第 605 句的译文
Everyone else didn't really have a navy. So everyone else is like,
...
we don't have a navy, but we'll contribute money.
Okay? And they agreed that
好的？他们又同意了
this money, this treasury,
这笔钱，这个仓库，
could only be used against Persia if Persia invades.
它只会在百里里…
Okay? So they put all this money on a place called Delos.
好的？他们把这笔钱放在一个叫德洛斯的地方。
Okay? An island called Delos.
好的？一个叫德洛斯的岛屿。
That's why it's called the Delian League.
因为它们才会有点…
All right? Does that make sense? So basically,
好的？这有道理吗？所以基本上，
Athens would put up a navy and everyone else would go back to Persia.
雅典会组建一支舰队，其他人则回到波斯。
And this money,
这笔钱，
this treasury of the Delian League can
这笔德洛斯联邦的国库可以只用来作战时的支出
only be used in a war against
这笔德尔奥斯的…
Persia. Okay?
此时…
Does that make sense? Okay.
好的吗？好吧。
So while this is happening,
于是这件事发生时，雅典...
Athens is the rising power in this world.
雅典是...
And in 461 BCE,
...
a new political leader called Pericles comes into power.
And as you should know from your research,
...
Pericles is considered the father of Athenian democracy.
帕提克斯被认为是雅典民主的奠基者。
He's the one who spreads democracy throughout Athens. And
他把雅典的民主传播到各处。随后，历史学家们把它当作…
historians today worship Pericles.
帕提克斯是个…
Okay? Pericles is considered one of the greatest leaders ever in Western history.
好的？帕提克斯被认为是西方历史上最伟大的领导者之一。
Okay? I'll talk more about Pericles
好的，帕提机里斯…??
and democracy in a minute.
...
But I want to show you
that Pericles was first and
...
foremost a politician who
was concerned about amassing and keeping power.
641. 关心于集聚与保持权力。
Does that make sense? So he did a lot of wonderful things for Athens.
642. 先前说的那句…??
But I want to show you these things that
…
he did, even though they seem great,
他做了，虽然看起来很棒，
they really were about him amassing power for himself.
他又是个很好的政治家。
Okay? So, Pericles was a great politician.
The first thing he did was he spread democracy to everyone.
第一个动作是把民主扩展到每个人。
Okay? He basically gave every citizen the right to vote.
好的，给每个公民投票权。
And you're like, okay, that's great.
而且…
Direct democracy. Athens creates democracy.
直接民主。雅典创建民主。
This is great. Right? But the reason why he did
这很不错，先前…
that was to change the balance of power in Athens.
这点…
So he basically represented the lower nobility versus the upper nobility.
于是他基本把下层贵族与上层贵族对立起来。
Right? Usually, the upper nobility has more power because it is the most powerful.
通常上层贵族更有权力，因其是最强者。
It has more money. Okay?
它有更多的钱。
It has more prestige. So
它有更多的声望。于是
the way for the lower nobility to defeat
下层贵族通过与人民结盟来取胜。
the upper nobility is by allying itself with the people.
Okay? Does
...
that make sense? And you do that by giving people the right to vote.
And so by doing this,
...
Pericles basically made himself king of Athens.
佩里克利基本把自己变成了雅典的国王。
Does that make sense? In fact, he stayed in power from the beginning until the end of the 20th century.
它们说的那句“可算吗？”…
From 461 to 429.
从 461 年到 先前 20 世纪…
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
好的？这样说通吗？好吧？
And to please the people even more,
再给人们更大的满足感，
he basically made corruption official.
他把它变成了正式的贪污
What he did that
什么是...
was very important was he basically took the money from Delos
...
and brought it to Athens.
Basically, Pericles said to the Delian League, you know what?
基本上，佩里克斯说给了他俩?
This money in Delos, it's a lot of money.
把这点儿…
I'm afraid that the Persians will come and steal it, so let's take it to Athens.
...
Okay? When he brought it to Athens,
好的？他把它送到雅典后，他又把它花完了。
the next thing he did was he spent all of it.
好的，算起这点儿…
Okay? He built a lot of really impressive buildings,
好的，算起…
including something called the Parthenon.
包括一个叫帕台农的东西。
The Parthenon is this great temple to Athena,
帕台农是个很大…
which is a patron goddess of Athens.
此时…
They made the Athenian statue out of gold.
他们把雅典的雕像做成金色的。
Okay? They spent billions and billions of dollars on this temple.
好的，算起…
The reason why is when you do that, right, you give people jobs.
好的…
And you give people who support you money.
683: 1行 1句…
Okay? So this is basically official corruption.
]}We need to translate cues 683-685. Provide JSONarray translations. Let's translate each cue. 683:
Now, there are people in the upper nobility who
， wait cue 683:
thought what Pericles was doing was terrible for Athens.
...
And basically, in meetings, they wanted to ostracize Pericles.
? ..??????
Right? They accused Pericles of corruption,
..??..???
of basically bribing the city of Athens.
...
And they said, you are corrupting our morals.
Okay? You are hurting our democracy.
...
Therefore, we want to ostracize you.
因此我们要把你放逐出城。
And there was this vote against Pericles.
而且有个投票投给了。
And what happens? Do you guys know?
我们来回顾一下！
The people voted to exile Pericles' opponents.
人们投票把佩里克利斯的对手流放出去。
Okay? Those who criticized Pericles were now exiled.
好？ 先前批评佩里克利斯的人们现在已把他放逐出城。
They were exiled from Athens.
他们从阿尔特里斯的那点里去！
Therefore, Pericles no longer has any political opponents.
因此，佩里克利斯已无再有政治对手。
And Pericles can do whatever he wants.
佩里克利斯可以随意做事。
And so, the two big innovations of Pericles is democracy.
于是，佩里克里斯的两大创新是…
Okay? Right?
好？对吗？
Let's give people the right to vote.
让我们给人们投票的权利。
And let's give people more money. Okay?
再给人们更多的钱。
But also, empire.
但也有帝国。
The reason why is after Pericles basically stole the money,
原因是因为佩里克利斯基本上把钱抢走了，
the money was stolen. So, the people who were exiled from the Delian League, the allies were obviously angry.
钱已被抢走，
You stole our money. So, we are out of this league.
你们抢了我们的钱。于是我们离开了这支联盟。
And Pericles said, well, if you leave our league,
“我方”里边?…??…?????????????????????翻??…??…??…?????…??-??…??…??…??…??…?????…??????????…??…???…?????????1?……??……..?????…………………………………………………
we're going to come and invade you. So,
………………
Athens started this expansionist campaign
雅典开始了这场扩张运动
in order to maintain its empire.
以便于维持其帝国
So, the Delian League basically became the Athenian Empire.
于是，德利安联盟基本上成为了雅典的帝国
And now, Athens got basically 20% of its revenue from the Athenians.
And now, Athens got basically 20%of its revenue from the Athenians.
So, it's allies. Okay?
所以，盟友们。好吧？
Does that make sense? So, that's what Pericles was doing.
它们是否能给我方??
He was promoting democracy in order to make sure people voted for him.
他在推动民主，以确保人们投票给他。
He was promoting empire in order to
他在推动…
maintain the easy money flow into Athens.
保持资金流入雅典的便利。
Empire is important because remember,
保持流入雅典的资金流动。
Athens has a culture of eudaimonia.
雅典拥有幸福文化。
So, empire makes the rich extremely rich.
雅典拥有 eudaimonia 文化。
Extremely wealthy. You understand?
极其富裕。你明白吗？
Empire makes everyone rich, but it makes the wealthy even more so.
帝国使人人富足，却又让富者更富。
And so, the lower nobility, okay,
和……下层贵族，好吧，
the lower nobility became very jealous.
和下层贵族，好的！
And so, the way to resolve this issue is the lower nobility could choose to invade other places.
和……好吧，...
Okay? And if they win, they could make a lot of money for themselves.
...
So, one place they chose to invade was Egypt.
于是，选择了一个地点去发起发起发起...
But that failed. Okay? So, throughout this time,
...
you had a lot of Athenian expeditions throughout the world in looking to conquer new territory.
And sometimes they succeeded, but a lot of times they failed as well.
...
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
So, as Athens is expanding and
...
becoming much wealthier, other Greek colonies,
变得更富裕，其他希腊殖民，其他希腊政策开始对雅典发怒。好吧？雅典基本是大老大。
other Greek policies start to get angry at Athens.
变得更富裕，其他希腊殖民…
Okay? And Athens is basically the big bully.
??
They were afraid of Persia before.
他们曾经常害怕波斯之前。
But Persia didn't really bother the Greeks.
但波斯里边的那点儿很久?
Whereas, Athens was a big bully.
其…
They wanted to control all of Greece.
??
Okay? They basically were a mafia organization
OK? 这点…
that was forcing these islands
??
and the Aegean Sea to pay tribute to Athens.
和爱琴海支付给雅典的贡金。
And they were trying to take more territory from other Greek policies.
他们正尝试着去取的去的去…
So, in 431,
745: So, in 1…
the Greek policies united around Sparta
? 1..?????..??
and started something called the Peloponnesian War.
和开始了一个叫做“帕洛波尼亚战争”的事情。
Okay? And historically,
好的，先前…
what most historians will tell you is this war was started
749：大多数历史学家会说这场战争是因为...
because Sparta was afraid of
749-1：先前…
an emerging Athens.
正在崛起的雅典
Okay? Sparta was the hegemon.
好的？雅典已成为霸主
Sparta was the most dominant power in Greece at that time.
斯巴达在那时是希腊最强大之力。
And now that Athens was ruined. And now that Athens was rising,
斯巴达...??
Sparta felt threatened by Athens and therefore
斯巴达感到雅典威胁，于是宣布对雅典开战。
declared war on Athens.
那不对，先前…】}We need to translate cues 755-757. Provide Chinese subtitles.Use line breaks natural. Provide array translations. Let's craft. 755:
That's not true. Okay? That's not the reason.
? Let's produce.755:
The reason why is because Athens was an empire
因为雅典是个帝国，才有这个原因。
and it was going around and bullying everyone.
它在四处环绕，四个回环回到回…
And so, you didn't have a choice in the matter.
…
You got to fight Athens now or wait for Athens to invade you.
761. 现在要打雅典，还是等着它入侵。
Okay? So, it was because
762. 先………??
Athens was an imperial power.
763. 先前……??
And so, other nations had to, other Greek powers had no choice but to stand against
And so, other nations had to, other Greekpowers had no choice but to stand against
Athens. Okay? And Athens was an imperial power because
???
of its theory of eudaimonia.
]}
Okay? So, the great irony here,
767. 先……??
and you will see this pattern repeat itself throughout history,
768?
is the thing, the culture that
???
allows a nation to rise, okay, and this is eudaimonia,
.?????????????????????????????????????????????????????
will also cause it to decline.
将会导致它的衰落。
Does it make sense? Okay?
它的确很久?
Because it's because of the Peloponnesian War, which
因为...??
lasts from about 431
]?????????????????????????????????? 1??????? 2???? 3???? 4? 5???????? ???????? ???????? ????? ?????? ??????????????????????????????????????? ?????? ??????????????? ???JSON??????????????????? [?????????????????????????????????????????????????????????………..?????..????????..??..???…??…???…..??…..??………………??……..??…..………?…..??…..??..??..??..???……..??……..??..??..
BC to 404 BCE,
??
27 years, that Athens loses its empire.
Okay? So, the culture, eudaimonia,
OK? 先前的...??
that causes Athens to rise will ultimately lead to its decline as well.
...
All right? So, are you guys clear so far?
}]
Okay. So, please let me know if this is clear to you,
OK? 先前………???????????????????????????????…??…????????…?????…????????…??……????????…??…??………??…?????..?????..??..??..??..??..??..??..?????..??..??..???……??………??…..??..??..??……..??..??..???…..??..??..???……??…?????..??..??………??…..…..??..??..???…..??..??..??..……..??..??…???…..??..??…....??…..???…..??..??..1??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??………..??…..……..??…..??..??……..……..??…..??……..
if you have any questions before I continue.
??
Okay. So, even
OK
though Sparta and Athens are now at war with each other,
翻译
this war, again,
...
should have been pretty easily won by Athens.
Why? What can Athens do to destroy Sparta?
Why? What can Athensdo to destroy Sparta?
Okay. Do you guys know? What can Athens do,
OK? 先后? 先后??
really easy, to destroy Sparta?
...
Hellas, right? The Athenians have ships.
赫拉斯，对吗？雅典人有船。
They can choose to do what the Persians should have done, but
赫拉斯...????????????????????????????????????????????…
they didn't do, which is to basically take its navy,
他们没做的就是把它的海军放在海岸上，配合其…
land its navy on the coast, and support the Hellas in the rebellion.
...
Okay? If that would have happened, Sparta would have been destroyed very quickly.
好的？如果那样发生，斯巴达会很快被毁灭。
The Athenians didn't do that. All right?
好的，先后？
Do you understand? The Athenians didn't do that.
你明白吗？雅典人没这么做。
Now, Sparta, to counter this threat against Athens,
现在，斯巴达为了抵消这场对雅典的威胀，去…
what should it have done to counter this threat from Athens?
...
Exactly. Thank you. Okay? Its only option in this scenario is to free the Hellas
and save the Hellas before they fight for us against Athenians.
和…再把希腊前往去…
We will give you your liberty.
We … ...
Okay? And the Hellas would have been, yeah,
OK? 先后……
let's go fight for the Spartans.
让我们去打工…
Okay? So, Sparta would have increased its army ten times,
...
and it could have destroyed Athens.
和它可能会摧毁雅典。
Sparta didn't do this either.
斯帕特拉也没有这么做。
Okay? Do you understand?
OK? 先后…
So, from a military strategy perspective,
the way the Peloponnesian War didn't make any sense.
...
The only way to understand what happened is to understand
that the very basis of conflict in society is between the upper nobility
that ... ... ...
and the lower nobility.
和下层贵族
Okay? Do you understand?
OK? 先后…
The upper nobility is only interested in maintaining the status quo.
上层贵族只在意保持现状
They're very conservative. They don't like wars because
他们很保守。 他们只要点儿…
you could lose wars, and also because if you win wars,
...
you have people who are now richer than you are.
你现在有比你更富有的人。
Okay? So, the upper nobility is very conservative in both Athens and Sparta.
好的？在阿特斯与斯帕特里都很久的…
The lower nobility can only become
下层贵族只能通过战争或革命成为上层贵族
upper nobility through war or revolution.
下层贵族只可通过战争或革命才可成上层贵】}We need to translate cues 818-819. Provide two translations. Ensure Chinese natural. Use preferred terms? Not needed. Provide exactly two strings. Ensure no extra keys. Let's craft. 818:
Okay? So, they're always looking to upset the status quo.
好的？所以他们总是想打乱现状。
So, even though this war is going on, internally,
好的，...
there's still conflict between the upper nobility and the lower nobility.
有点儿………………??
Okay? And that's why, if you look at the Peloponnesian War,
]}We need to translate cues 822-823. Provide two translations. Let's produce. 822:
a lot of the military strategy doesn't make any sense because
好的？所以他们总是想打乱现状。
Sparta isn't really trying to win a war against Athens.
好的？于是战争进行中，内部仍有上层贵族与下层贵族的冲突。
Sparta is trying to maintain peace.
斯巴达正试着保持和平。
So, the upper nobility is losing the status quo in Sparta.
上层贵族在斯巴达里边缘?
Okay? Athens is not really trying to win a war against Sparta.
...
Athens is trying to maintain the status quo within Athens.
Alright? An example is Pericles.
...
The war starts in 431 B.C.
and a lot of people are saying, Pericles, hey, let's go invade Sparta.
和许多人说：佩里克利斯，嘿，去侵入斯巴达吧。
And what Pericles says instead is, oh no no no.
佩里克利的回声是：又是………
The Spartans are the greatest warriors in the world.
“可是…………”，…
We have no chance against Sparta.
我们有墙壁，...
So, what we'll do is.
...
is we have these walls, okay?
We have these walls, we'll hide behind our walls
我们有这些墙，等我们在墙后隐藏，
and let our navy protect us in the sea, okay?
我们在墙后隐藏，等………
That was the defensive strategy of Pericles.
我们在墙后…………
And so what the Spartans could do was they could come to Attica
于是，斯巴达人可以去阿提卡，然后再把所有农田毁掉。
and destroy all the farmland.
阿提卡里，斯巴达人可以把农田全部消失。
And the Athenians could only watch as the Spartans destroy the farmland.
...
This was a disaster for the Athenians
这对雅典人来说是一次灾难
because if you think about it, over time,
因为如果你想一想，算算时间…
the Spartans could starve out the Athenians, right?
雅典人可算…
The other problem is you have too many people in one place, what happens?
另一件事就是，城市里有太多的人，发生了什么？
You have too many people living in a city, what happens usually?
城市里有太多人，通常会出现什么？
Disease, right? Disease.
疾病！
So because of the overpopulation,
因为过度人口，雅典人有了疣病
in Athens, they had the plague,
在此时…
which killed one third of the Athenian population.
此时…
Okay, do you understand? One third of the Athenian population.
If the Athenians went to war against Sparta
...
and they lost,
they would have at most lost about 10% of their population.
他们会在此时…
But because they chose not to fight and
他们………………
hide behind the walls, not only did they lose their farmland,
……… … … … … … ?
but they lost a third of their population.
但他们失去了三分之一的人口。
Including Pericles, who died because of the plague.
包括帕里克斯，他因瘟疫而亡。
Pericles died as well as his two sons, okay?
帕里克斯与他的两子也相继相亡。
Doesn't make sense, right?
不太对劲，吧？
So again, this strategy makes no sense.
又一次…………………………………………………
If you think from a military perspective,
]}We need to translate cues [862] and [863] and [864] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translationsin order. Each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use natural Chinese. Let's translate: [862]
it only makes sense if you understand
它只有在你理解……时才有意义
there's an internal conflict in Athens between the upper nobility and the lower nobility, okay?
有上层贵族与下层贵族之间的内部冲突，正如你所说……？
Pericles represents the upper nobility, he wants to maintain the status quo.
帕里克斯代表上层贵族，他要去维护…
There's a war going on, and he wants to maintain the status quo.
有一场战争正在进行，他想保持现状。
But he doesn't really want to fight this war, okay?
他还没能好好去战斗…………………
He just wants to wait it out because he does not want to change the status quo.
他只想等待……………
Okay, does that make sense? So,
好的，明白了。
after Pericles dies,
在帕里克斯去世后，
the lower nobility become ascendant, okay?
在帕里宫…
And because of this war,
因为这场战争，
they propose an aggressive strategy against the Spartans.
他们提出了对斯巴达的进攻策略。
Basically, it's like, let's go attack the Spartans.
基本上就是，先攻打斯巴达。
And cause a revolution in Sparta, okay?
在帕里克斯去世后，
And this was proposed by Cleon,
在帕里宫…
who after Pericles died,
became basically the de facto leader of Athens.
变成了雅典的实际领袖。
And he was considered a demagogue, okay?
他被认为是个民众领袖，行吗？
If you look at the history, everyone says bad things about this guy, okay?
若要看史书，皆说他好像是个好事人。
But really, what he is,
但确实是他所做的事，
he's lower nobility who's trying to achieve eudaimonia, okay?
他是个下层贵族，正在尝试去实现…
And he's basically like, from Mexico, please.
…从…??
Okay? Alright?
OK?
And he's a great military strategist as well.
他又是个很好的…??
So, Cleon proposes this aggressive strategy against Sparta,
??
and guess what happens? Athens is now destroying Sparta.
和猜猜什么会发生？雅典现在正好消灭了斯巴达。
Okay? Now, Sparta is under a lot of pressure.
好的，……………??
It's losing the war. So,
它正在失去战争。于是，
now what Sparta does is,
??
it picks a new general, Brasidas.
它挑选了一个新将军，布拉西达斯。
And says to Brasidas, listen, we're losing the war, what can we do?
它们说给布拉西达本身…
So, Brasidas goes north,
于是，布拉西达斯北上，并开始在对阵雅典的战役中取胜。
and he starts winning his victories against Athens.
and he starts winning hisvictories against Athens.
And his policy is this, listen,
他的方法是这样：听着，
we need to change our social structure in order to win against Athens.
我们要把我们的社会结构改成这样，才能赢得对雅典的战斗。
So, what he does is he tells the helots, if you fight for me, I'm going to give you your freedom.
于是，他告诉赫洛特们，如果你们为我而战，我就给你们自由。
And so, a lot of helots fight for Brasidas, and Brasidas wins a lot of wars.
于是，赫尔奥特们战斗…
And this is what happens. And how do the Spartans feel about this?
而这就是发生的事。斯巴达人对此有何感受？
Brasidas, who's a Spartan, is now winning wars against Athens.
布拉西达斯，身为斯巴达人，正赢得对雅典的战斗。
And so, how do the Spartans feel about this?
于是，斯巴达人此时又回到…
Are they happy about this? No,
他们对此满意吗？不，他们真的很不满意。
they're really unhappy about this, okay?
他们的确是个别的…
Because it's changing their social structure.
此时…
You understand? They don't want this crap.
你明白了吗？他们不想要这玩意。
They want the helots to be slaves.
他们想让赫洛特成为奴隶。
They don't want the helots to be free citizens.
他们想让赫洛特成为自由公民。
They want free citizens who help them win wars, okay?
So, what ultimately happens is, even though
译文
Cleon and Brasidas have both proposed strategies
...
that allow Athens and Sparta to win the war,
翻译后可用????????????????????????????????????????????????
ultimately, what happens is Cleon
...
and Brasidas get into a battle with each other, and they both die in this battle.
and Brasidas get into a battle with eachother, and they both die in this battle.
That's extremely convenient, guys, okay?
...
That's really, really convenient.
{
So, I'd be very surprised if they actually did both die in battle.
...
My guess is what happened is they were both assassinated during the battle against each other.
Does that make sense? Because ultimately,
both were the bigger threats to the social structure of Sparta
921: 921-...
and Athens than losing the war itself.
1221?
Does that make sense, guys? Okay?
...
Any questions so far?
Okay. Does that make sense?
好的。听得懂吗？
Okay. Okay.
好的。好的。
So, now,
...
so this war keeps on going,
and then what happens is the Persia gets involved
和...之后，波斯就会参与，随后给了斯巴达一支舰队。
and gives Sparta a navy.
波斯里边给了斯巴达舰队
Basically, Persia gives Sparta a blank check.
基本上，波斯给了斯巴达一笔空白支票。
And because Sparta is so conservative and insular,
???
it doesn't really know how to, you know,
它不太懂怎么做，知道吗？
have a navy, okay? It doesn't know how to fight with a navy.
有点船，好的？它没能去做船呢？
In fact, Sparta is militarily, like,
在这点上…
in terms of strategy, it's actually very weak, okay?
??
If it's, like, Spartan soldiers by themselves are very strong,
but in terms of, like, overall military strategy,
??
Sparta, because it's so conservative and insular, it's very weak,
斯巴达因为很保守且内向，故很弱。
again, it's very weak compared with Athens.
再一次，斯巴达比亚里斯比…...】}We need to translate cues 939-941. Provide Chinese subtitles. Use given terms. Let's translate. 939:
But Persia has a lot of money, and Persia is bankrolling Sparta, okay?
? Let's produce.939:
And eventually, Persia says to Sparta, hey, guys.
??
Why don't you try a new strategy?
The strategy is this. If a general is winning against the Athenians,
??
promote the guy, okay?
但凡尔萨里亚里有多钱，且……
And you're like, okay, well, that makes total sense.
...………??…???
The Spartans didn't do that, okay?
…………???
The Spartans were not concerned about winning the war.
斯巴达人并不在乎赢得战争
They were concerned about maintaining their social order.
他们只要去做个别的??
Do you understand? There's a social hierarchy in Sparta.
我想要...??
That's what's important, not winning the war.
那是个好点子！
And then there was a Spartan commander,
...??…?????
Lysander. And
...???????
he was really the only Spartan who
他是斯巴达的唯一一位能胜战的海军指挥者。
knew how to win naval battles.
他在百里里??????????????????????????????????????????
The problem with Lysander was he was a half -citizen,
]}We need to translate cues 954-956. They are: [954] he was really the only Spartan who[955] knew how to win naval battles. [956] The problem with Lys... etc. Actually 956 is
which meant
哪一…??
that his father was a Spartan
...??…???
but not the mother. Do you understand?
...??????
Only if both your parents are citizens are you allowed to be a citizen.
只有当你父母都是公民时，方可成为公民。
So Lysander was really looked down upon in Sparta.
斯拉斯特里亚????????????????
But he could win naval battles.
...
So he wasn't promoted.
他没有被提升。
The Persians said to the Spartans, listen, this is stupid, okay?
波斯人对斯巴达说：听着，算了吧！
Lysander is a great commander.
拉斯特里亚是个大司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司司??
You have to promote him.
你得把他提拔到位。
The Spartans didn't really have a choice in the matter.
??????????????????????????????????????
And so Lysander, after he was promoted,
???..?????..???????????..?????..????????..??..??..????????????
single -handedly won the war against Athens.
??
He laid siege to Athens in 404 BCE.
他在公元前404年对雅典展开围攻。
And then Athens had no choice
...
but to surrender because they were out of food, okay?
Does that make sense? Now,
???
for 27 years,
for 27 years ... ?? ??????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????
Sparta and Athens were at war with each other.
??
They were killing each other. Now Athens had finally been defeated.
他们在相互相杀。 现在，雅典 …
So what do you think should happen now?
}]
What should happen to Athens now?
...
Okay, the answer is nothing happened to Athens, okay?
OK?
Usually if you lose a war, in this world,
通常在这场战争中，若你失去胜利，后就会出现…
what happens is they come and kill all the men and enslave all the women.
在这场…
And that's what the Persians wanted, okay?
那就是帕萨里人想要的，好的？
That's what the other Greek cities wanted to happen to Athens.
那是…
The Spartans didn't do anything to Athens.
帕萨里人没有对雅典做任何事。
They left Athens alone, okay?
帕萨里人留给了他。”
And there are many different explanations for this.
还有许多种解释
One explanation is Sparta wanted to maintain a balance of power in the Greek world,
一条可用来写作…
okay? They destroyed Athens, then Persia could come back and destroy Sparta, okay?
好的，帕萨里...
But another explanation is, well, guess what, guys?
...
The upper nobility of Sparta and the upper nobility of Athens,
帕萨里人上层贵族与帕萨里人上层贵族，彼此相互好，好的？
they're good friends with each other, okay?
帕萨里人上层贵族与帕-
Do you understand? Rich people tend to marry each other.
992: 译文1
They tend to be good friends with each other, okay?
...
So Athens and
Sparta weren't really enemies,
帕萨里人不是很久的敌人，
do you understand? They had to fight this war because
你们好吗？他们要去打这场战斗，
of the internal pressures from the lower nobility.
因为帕里斯里里…
Because this war was killing off so much lower nobility, it maintained the status quo.
因为这场战争的回归归回归…
Does that make sense? All right?
...
You guys understand so far? Any questions?
All right. So I'm going to conclude with evidence for you.
翻译1
I'm going to give you some evidence for this theory, okay?
]}
So what I just said, like,
翻...??
war is really about killing off internal dissent,
war … … … … … … {
not really about beating the other enemy.
…………………
That's very controversial, okay? So I will give you some evidence for this theory,
… … … ..……
and it's called rat utopia.
并且被称为“鼠乌托邦”。
So in the 1960s and 70s,
于是，在1960年代和70年代，
there was an American researcher, American scientist.
有一位美国研究员，来自美国的科学家。
His name is James U.
他的名字是詹姆斯·U。
He was engaged in wartime
他在战争期间从事工作。
engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged
engaged engaged
已完成的工作
engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged engaged Well he couldn't really experiment on humans,
so he decided to experiment on rats instead.
已完成的工作
So he built this universe, basically this big house,
于是他建造了这个宇宙，基本上就是这座大房子，食物对老鼠来说很充足。
and food was plentiful for rats.
食物与水源对老鼠来说都很充足。
The food, the water was plentiful for rats.
So rats could just play all day.
...
Now I'm not sure if you know anything about rats, but
the thing about animals, and this is a very important idea,
...
is that animals live in
动物们居住在
a heavily ritualized
重 好 好 好！
and rules -based world.
此 好 好 好！
It doesn't make sense, guys. We think of animals as chaotic, no, no, no.
它不太对，兄弟们。我们把动物看成乱序的，才没得…
If you actually study their society, ants, monkeys, rats,
...
they live in an extremely rule -based,
heavily ritualized world, okay?
重 句好好好！
So let me give you an example of this.
例句好！
So rats, when they mate with each other, what happens is this.
...
A female rat is interested in having sex, okay?
一只雌鼠对交配产生兴趣，好的？
So she's going out, and then a male rat spots this.
她正好去外面去，咱们…
He sees the female rat in heat.
他看到雌鼠在热…
So what he does is he gets on a mound, okay, where
他在堆上起舞，随后她看见他，开始舞蹈。
she can see him, and he starts to dance, okay?
{
He starts to dance. And
?
the female rat becomes interested, and
雌鼠产生兴趣，随后他看到她，随后又回到…
he sees, she's interested, so
他在……
he comes down, and they start chasing each other, okay?
他人……
They're having fun together. And then what she does is she runs home
他们一起玩得很开心。然后她跑回家去
and hides herself in her burrow.
她在回到回到…
The male rat just stands outside and waits for her to come out.
他在…
After some time, she comes out, and they run together again, and then she runs back again.
在某段时间后，她又出来，跟着一起跑，随后又回到…
They do this many, many times until finally
在此后再多次…
she lets him catch him, and then they have sex.
…
Okay? And then after they have sex, they have children, and they start a family together, okay?
好的？然后它们交配后会生孩子，随后一起组建家庭，怎么样？
Does that make sense? Okay, that's how rats usually behave.
这有点儿意思吗？这就是鼠类的常见行为。
When they often like to play with each other, and they fight, but it's very playful, okay?
他们常常相互相互玩耍，咱们好玩又好玩。
So there's lots of rules, there's lots of rituals
在这只鼠类社会里有许多的规矩，许多的仪式
in this rat society, but that's out in nature.
在这只鼠类的规矩里，回到自然里
In the world of James B.
在约瑟·巴尔的世界
Calhoun, he creates a rat utopia, okay?
卡尔洪，他创造了一个鼠类乌托邦，怎么样？
Where everyone has enough to eat.
每个人都有足够吃的地方。
And at some point, the society breaks down, okay?
在某个时刻，社会就会崩溃。
These rituals, these rules all break down.
这些仪式，这些规则都崩溃了。
What happens is male rats,
当且当时，鼠类男士们在此时…
when they start fighting each other, they become very violent.
They're no longer playing, they're actually trying to kill each other, and some actually die, okay?
他们不再玩耍，实际上在互相打杀，甚至有时会死去。
And this mating ritual, it breaks down.
这场交配舞蹈已然后。
So the male rats don't even try to dance, okay?
男鼠们也不再去舞蹈。
They're not dancing. They just see a female, and they, you know, they're like, they rape her, okay?
他们不再舞蹈。只见一只雌鼠，便开始舞蹈，…………………??
And it's like gang rape. It's not one male, it's like lots of males raping her.
…… … …… …………………………………
These gangs of rats, they try to break into boroughs,
..??..
homes, and try to rape the wife, okay?
家里，去抢抢妻子吧？
The mother. And at first,
母亲，先前…
the husband is fighting off these other rats, right?
丈夫在打斗…
But eventually what happens is he gets tired,
但最终发生的事是他累了，
and he just runs away, okay?
他就跑了，好的？
He just abandons the family. Now the female rat is responsible for fighting off now the other rats.
他就把家族抛在了，现…
But she becomes so traumatized, she starts to beat everyone up, including her own children.
但她被打得很伤，开始打人家…
So she kicks her children out of the house.
...
It is a complete social breakdown.
And after a few more months of this crap,
几个月后，整个鼠群就……
the entire colony of rats dies.
整个鼠群的全体…
The entire society collapses.
...
Does that make sense? Alright?
So this is what we call rat utopia.
...
It's been done many times. And each time they do this, this happens.
At some point, this society will collapse.
在某个时刻，这个社会会崩溃。
Okay? And this makes no sense to us.
好的？这回合成了？
Everyone has enough food to eat.
每个别人都吃得好吃
Everyone should be happy, okay? Why does society collapse?
...
Okay, so there are different explanations for this.
好的，算吧！
James B. Calhoun, his argument is,
]}
if there's too much food, there's overpopulation.
如果食物太多，人口就会过多。
There's overpopulation, then that creates conflict.
有过多的人口，随后就会产生冲突。
And the conflict causes the rules to collapse, okay?
...
The problem, though, with this theory,
is the colony never became overpopulated, okay?
殖民未曾过度繁衢，已？
There was space for everyone.
有空位给每个？
But at some point, everyone started to fight each other.
但在某个时刻，大家开始互相争斗。
Alright? So this is my theory.
好的？这就是我的理论。
And this goes back to the Peloponnesian War.
和这回到伯罗奔尼亚战争。
It has to do with the idea of status.
它们回到伯尔奔尼亚战争？
So in a world of abundance,
在一个充足的世界里，
in a world of wealth, who benefits the most?
在一个充足的财富里，谁能在此中最先？
It's the elderly.
...
Older. Older people, okay?
老的...??
Old people can live a lot longer in a society
that is wealthy and abundant, okay?
那是富裕且充足的，好的？
Does that make sense? Okay?
那可算是...
But then what happens is the status becomes locked in,
翻译成中文
which prevents younger rats, younger people,
翻译结果
from ascending into power and status.
...
Does that make sense? Okay?
So the idea is,
翻译结果
the metaphor is, these rats are online, okay?
}]We need to translate cue 1107:
I'm waiting for, to climb the mountain, okay?
我正在等待...
This is the mountain top. You're waiting
...
and waiting to climb the mountain.
和等待爬山。
And everyone's moving along.
大家都在前进。
It's slow, but you're still moving along, okay?
...
And eventually you will reach the mountain top,
which is where you want to be. But
哪儿是你想去的地方。 但…
let's just say for whatever reason, the line stops moving, okay?
让我们来个别的…
And that's not a good thing. Everyone's stuck in place. Well then you get very anxious.
和那是好事。每个人都在回到回到…
You get very stressed out.
...
You get very agitated. You're like, when is it my turn?
你很激动。你会说：什么时候轮到我？
And it's never gonna come because the people at the top won't leave,
而且…
okay? So what do you do?
好的？那你做什么？
Well you start kicking the people behind you, right?
好吧，先开始给我方块…
You start fighting with each other.
你开始相互打斗。
You understand? That's what we call rat utopia.
你们懂了吗？…
In a world of abundance, in a world of extreme wealth,
在…
old people do not die.
老人不死。
If they do not die,
若老人不死，
it is impossible for young people to ascend into power and status.
And so they have all these energies.
又是它们的能量
And because they cannot reach their potential,
又相当时能量
they become violent and start attacking each other,
又相当能量？
okay? So that's rat utopia.
好的？那就是老鼠国度。
That's what rats do. But if you look at the Peloponnesian War
那可好！老鼠的那点儿！
and what happened between Athens and Sparta, it's really no different,
??
okay? It's really no different.
好的？其实没什么区别。
They were killing each other for no reason.
他们相互相杀，才是好！
Extreme violence, which led to nothing, okay?
极端相互相杀！
431 BCE,
431 BCE，在 404 BCE 之前的政治世界相同。
the political world was no different from 404 BCE.
在 431 B‑BCE 里，在 431 B‑B??…
The only difference is a lot of young people died, okay?
…
In wars against each other.
In ... … … … … {
So that's my argument to you. If societies become too wealthy,
1141: 1/2 译文
you have a problem of rat utopia,
1142??
okay?
好吧？
If rat utopia, societies will then
如果…
engage in wars
参与战争
that will lead eventually to its collapse.
最终导致其崩溃
And that's what happened to Athens.
安那样就发生在雅典。
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
好的，大家好吗？
All right, any questions about this?
好的，关于这点还有什么问题？
Does it make sense? Does it make sense to you guys?
它会变成…
All right? Any questions? Yeah.
1151: 1/2
Okay, so the question is,
]}We need to translate cues 1151 and 1152. Provide JSON array translations. Let's translate:
in the rat utopia,
在鼠乌托邦里，
why do the mothers want to start attacking the kids, okay?
在大鼠之中…
Okay, so this is actually a complicated question.
好的，...
The answer is this. Humans are different from rats, okay?
...
So humans have the ability to reason and
to adapt to new circumstances, okay?
适应新环境，OK？
Does that make sense? Rats don't.
这算是个好句？鼠标??
There are these rules in place, okay?
…
And if these rules are broken, then the rats don't know how to adapt.
如果这些规则被打破，老鼠就会失去适应之法。
So if you're a rat mother, you have a husband, okay?
又说：若是鼠标母亲，先前有个回归? ？
Your understanding is the husband will protect you from strangers,
?
okay? Okay?
好？好？
Okay? Your understanding is if someone is violent towards you,
好？你的理解是：若有人对你施暴，你就得对那人施暴，OK？
you have to be violent against that person, okay?
好！
So in a situation where the husband leaves,
在丈夫离开之时，
the husband runs away or is dead,
在丈夫跑去或去世之时，
the mother does not understand this new order anymore.
母亲不再领悟此新秩序。
So the mother becomes, the word we use is traumatized.
所以母亲变成了， 我们用的词是“受创伤”
You're traumatized, you can no longer reason, okay?
你们好像是“受创伤”
You're so focused on protecting yourself, you attack everything and everyone, including your own children.
其后…
Does that make sense? Yeah, this is an experiment because obviously this would not happen in real life, okay?
这有道理吗？是的，这是一场实验，显然在现实里会这么做吗？
There's no way the rats get free food in real life.
在这场实验里，没点儿…
So they have this experiment where the experimenters gave the rats free food every day.
这条…
And this is what happened..
译文1
No, no. So the experiment is.
译文2
The rats were left by themselves,
译句3
okay? The rats could do whatever they wanted.
好的？老鼠们可以随心所欲。
The only thing the experimenters did was feed them every day.
唯一的实验者所做的就是每天给它们喂食。
Okay? If you do that, if there's abundance and there's wealth,
好的？如果你做了这件事，若有丰盛与丰裕。
then you have complete social collapse.
然后你就有完整的社会崩溃。
Okay?.
好的？
Okay, okay, all right. So, okay, all you need to understand is this, okay?
好的，好的，全部好！...??
. So the entire society collapses.
. 整个社会坍塌。
Okay? How it collapses can be different from family to family.
好？坍塌的方式因家族而异。
So the entire society collapses. Everyone dies at the end.
整家社会坍塌。全部人终结。
Okay? Do you understand?
好的？你明白吗？
Okay. Any more questions? Any more questions?
好的。还有问题吗？还有问题吗？
So I know this is a very important question. I know this is a lot to take in, okay?
所以我知道这很重要。要领会的事多，先行吧。
This is very confusing and this is very hard,
这很有点儿很久?
but it's okay, just ask any questions or points
...】】】】】】】?】?】?】??】????????????????????????????????????????????????????????????{
where you want me to clarify.
?
Okay, so next class we will do Greek theater,
好的，下一节课我们先做希腊剧场，后面再做希腊哲学，包含帕洛特、苏尔特尔·帕洛特…?
and then after that we'll do Greek philosophy, which includes Plato,
??
Socrates, and Aristotle, okay?